Now that you have calculated
the transition probabilities,
you're ready to calculate
the emission probabilities
for the hidden Markov model.
As you might imagine,
the emission probabilities are
calculated in a very similar way.
Going back to your very
small training corpus,
which has the associated parts of
speech tags depicted by
the background color.
In contrast to the transition
probabilities here,
you would want to count
the co-occurrences of
a part of speech tag
with a specific word.
For example, the word
"you" appears two
times in your corpus,
tags with the blue
parts of speech tag,
and the blue parts of speech
tag appears three times.
So the emission probability
for the word "you",
following the blue parts of
speech tag is two-thirds.
Let's continue with a
more complicated example;
the haiku you processed
in the previous lesson.
You have the same tags and
can start to fill in the counts.
But instead of counting
pairs of tags,
you will now count
how often a word is
tagged with a specific
tag like noun, verb,
or the other tag like it is
shown in the first column
of the emission matrix for
the tag and the word "in".
The noun tag is associated
zero times with the word "in".
The verb tag is
associated zero times
with the word "into".
The O tag is
associated two times with
the word "in" in the corpus.
The formula with smoothing for
the emission probabilities B of
w_i given the tag
t_i for the word
is given by the counts
of t_i and the word
w_i divided by the
corresponding row sum
in the emission matrix,
which is the same as dividing by
the total counts of the tag, t_i,
with capital N
being the number of
tags and capital V being
the size of our vocabulary.
To recap, you now can
calculate both
transition and emission
matrices and also apply
smoothing for better
generalization of the model.
You've come a long way
this week. Great work.
Given these two matrices,
you will now learn
how to use them
together in order for you to
compute the parts of speech
tags of a given sentence.